<!-- index.xml {% comment %}
*****************************************************************************************
*                            WARNING: DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE                             *
*                                                                                       *
* This file is generated by SUSHI. Any edits you make to this file will be overwritten. *
*                                                                                       *
* To change the contents of this file, edit the original source file at:                *
* genomics-reporting/input/pages/index.xml                                              *
*****************************************************************************************
{% endcomment %} -->
<div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://hl7.org/fhir ../../src-generated/schemas/fhir-single.xsd">

  <a name="scope"> </a>
  <h3>Scope</h3>
  <p>
A single Adverse Event may need to be reported in multiple ways. Choosing the appropriate form of the reporting is dependent upon workflow patterns. In particular, the implementation guides for Clinical Care adverse events  and Clinical Research adverse events  provide important extensions, value-sets and examples for implementing AdverseEvent.
</p>
  <p>
    This guide, the Clinical Research adverse event implementation guide, is for the clinical research setting.  The event is tracked and evaluated as part of the clinical research process  for the research study, since the occurrence of an adverse event may surface a potential confounder or a potential side-effect of the study treatment. 
  </p>
  <p>
    In the research setting an adverse event is the result of an intervention that caused unintentional harm to a specific subject or group of subjects, potential adverse events are not reported (this is surfaced in the profile as a constraint of ‘actual’ for the value of ‘actuality’). Examples of adverse events include the administration of an incorrect drug or an incorrect dose of a drug causing an adverse reaction, the use of an implanted device that causes an infection, or a biologic used during a research study that causes unanticipated renal failure. These events are characterized by the need to capture cause-and-effect (although they might not be known at the time of the event), severity, and outcome. 
  </p>
  <p>
  The context of an adverse event is also important. A subject may have condition(s) or current treatments (medications, diet, devices) that impact their response to a newly introduced medication, device or procedure. Knowledge of these variables is essential in establishing a cause-and-effect relationship for an adverse event. Additionally, steps to mitigate the harm or resolve the event are recorded.
  </p>
  <p>
  A potential adverse event may also be called a near miss or an error. These are also events, but since they were detected, did not cause harm to a subject. Examples of potential adverse events include a product problem such as a faulty pacemaker that is detected prior implantation, a doctor working simultaneously on two electronic health records realizing the order for a drug was entered on the incorrect patient and then canceling the order, or a patient with a peanut allergy notices that his hospital dinner tray includes peanuts, and he does not eat the peanuts. Near miss events like this are not reported with the AdverseEvent Clinical Research profile.
  </p>
  <p>
  Within this guide are several examples. Every effort has been made to capture the most important details of the use of the AdverseEvent profile. However, some examples may provide only a stub to referenced resources (e.g. instances of Patient Resource will be referenced using logical ids but are not resolvable, implementation of Patient is left for other guidance and is not the subject of this guide). Connectathons are ideal opportunities to create, compare and consider the holistic implementation of all FHIR Resources.
  </p>
  <p>
  For examples and further guidance, it is strongly suggested that an implementer consult the Clinical Care AdverseEvent Implementation Guide  and the Clinical Research AdverseEvent Implementation Guide  They contain valuable extensions, value sets and, importantly, examples. 
  </p>

  <a name="how to use this guide"> </a>
  <h3>How to Use this Guide</h3> 
  <p>
  This implementation guide is focused on the use of the <a href="StructureDefinition-AdverseEvent-clinical-research.html">AdverseEvent Resource in Clinical Research</a>. When reviewing profiles begin with the snapshot view to understand the entire set of data elements and rules for implementation. The differential does no show elements unchanged from the parent, in the snapshot constraints inherited from the parent are visible. Those new to FHIR should review the Understanding FHIR section below.
  </p>
  
  <a name="previous"> </a>
  <h3>Previous Specifications</h3>
  <p>
    FHIR STU4 contained a non-normative version of the AdverseEvent Resource. The specification here is based on changes made in R5 and supersedes the use of the R4 Resource.
  </p>
  <a name="fhir"> </a>
  <h3>Understanding FHIR</h3>
  <p>
    This implementation guide is based on the HL7 <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}index.html">FHIR</a> standard. It uses terminology, notations and design principles that are specific to FHIR. Before reading this implementation guide, it's important to be familiar with some of the basic principles of FHIR as well as general guidance on how to read FHIR specifications. Readers who are unfamiliar with FHIR are encouraged to read (or at least skim) the following prior to reading the rest of this implementation guide.
  </p>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview.html">FHIR overview</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview-dev.html">Developer's introduction</a>
    </li>
    <li>(or <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}overview-clinical.html">Clinical introduction</a>)</li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}datatypes.html">FHIR data types</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}terminologies.html">Using codes</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}references.html">References between resources</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}formats.html">How to read resource &amp; profile definitions</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}resource.html">Base resource</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="{{site.data.fhir.path}}validation.html">FHIR Validation</a>
    </li>
  </ul>

  <a name="flexibility"> </a>
  <h3>Extending beyond this Guide</h3>
  <p>
    Implementers should use this guide to AdverseEvent Clinical Research communications in an interoperable way. It is understood that this guide is not complete, and implementers might identify additional concepts and data elements. Please review this <a href="general.html#flexibility">guidance</a> for ways to handle those use cases. Additionally, it is recommended that additional Implementation Guides should be adapted from this one as a base for tighter specifications such as in oncology clinical trials.
  </p>

  <a name="acknowledgments"> </a>
  <h3>Acknowledgments</h3>
  <p>
    The Clinical Research Adverse Event Implementation Guide is a product of the <a href="">HL7 Patient Care Work Group</a>. Questions or comments regarding this implementation guide should be directed to Patient Care at <a href="mailto:patientcare@lists.hl7.org">patientcare@lists.hl7.org</a>. 
  </p>
  <p>
    The authors of this guide wish to recognize the following participants who contributed their time and expertise to the continued development of this guide:
  </p>

</div>
